So we started our journey at University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign. We got the
NSF, created University of Michigan, we created the web, we created the first web
server, and now we're going to come back to where we started. We're going to go
back to the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. These are the folks
that basically exploded the web, moved the web from the academic space to the
commercial and end user space. And there's all kinds of things. The network
was growing, things were getting faster, personal computers were getting better
very rapid pace because the IBM PC is almost 10 years old and many computers
and they were getting quite fast in the in the 90s. So the 1990s our computing
and their display capabilities were getting better very rapidly. And in this
environment NCSA at Urbana-Champaign, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign
built an open source web browser that worked on Mac, Windows, and Unix. It was
the first web browser that did this and it it was the thing that really made it
so average people who had PCs or Macs in their home could get a network
connection and start enjoying all of this new content that was coming up on
the world wide web. Hello my name is Charles Severance and I am showing you
right now a desktop application that works on my Macintosh called NCSA X
Mosaic. This was software released in 1993 and it was the first Mosaic. It was
the X Windows Mosaic and I'm running it on my Macintosh and you can download it
from my github account. CSAB is my github handle and it's the X Mosaic - 1.2
So what we're looking at here is the original default homepage at the
National Center for Supercomputing Applications at the University of
Illinois and we see it as we saw it circa 1993. We can scroll through we can
see the old good old days the visited links in purple and so if we scroll
down you'll see some neat pictures and the wonderful gray background. List tags
were real back then. You know we can go see something about visualization at
NCSA. I've done a little tiny bit to this to teach it a few things. You can see
all that I've done on HTTP on my github site. You can see everything I've done on
my github site. I try to stay as I just made a few more things work like PNG
images and HTTP 1.1 seek it to visit more more pages. Another another
wonderful page to another wonderful page to take a look at is the original first
page on the world wide web the info.cern.ch and again we're experiencing
it now circa 1993 to see what's out there. Take a look at the people involved
in the project. So here's some of those pages Tim Berners-Lee of course Robert
Caillou of course and here's some of the other people that were working at CERN.
So there you go that is a quick experience in how we surf the web in 1993.
After this the NCSA staff student programmers software developers all
formed the company Netscape in order to commercialize all this. Joseph Harden
was the supervisor of the software development group at NCSA that was
responsible for building and releasing both the mosaic web browser and the
HTTP web server as open source and gave them away free.